Finding Aid for Safford and Sunderland Family Papers 1826-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Safford and Sunderland Family papers 1826-1987 1890-1940
Safford family.
The Safford Sunderland papers trace several generations of a Southeastern Michigan family, showcasing everyday life and Michigan (as well as U.S.) history over the course of the first half of the Twentieth Century.
03161 Aa 2 UAm
6.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Gertrude Sunderland Safford's granddaughter Janet Toohy Ferguson (donor no. 9192 ) in 2002.
The collection is open for research.
The Sunderland and Safford families have been an influential presence in Michigan history. The Safford family came to Michigan from the East Coast in the first half of the nineteenth century, and have deep roots in the Plymouth/Canton Township area. Several Safford cousins enlisted in the Michigan 24th Infantry during the Civil War; the collection includes the letters of Winfield Scott Safford to his brother Robert Crawford Safford. (Winfield Scott Safford was killed in action at Gettysburg, July 1st, 1863.) The Sunderlands, meanwhile, first came to Ann Arbor in 1878, as a result of the pastorate of prominent Unitarian Minister Jabez T. Sunderland (1846-1936). (Sunderland was pastor of the First Unitarian Church in Ann Arbor from 1878 to 1898.) During that period, the Sunderland's eldest daughter Gertrude (1873-1967) met Robert Crawford Safford's son, Homer Erwin Safford (1869-1933). Homer Safford and Gertrude Sunderland married in 1898.
This collection is comprised primarily of the papers of Homer E. and Gertrude S. Safford, their daughters Mildred H. Safford (1901-) and Helen Safford Toohy (1899-1997), and of Homer Safford's sister, Ada Murray Safford (1877-1951). Many of the Saffords and Sunderlands (and Sunderland Saffords) have connections to the University of Michigan: Gertrude Sunderland Safford received an AB in 1895, Homer E. Safford a PhB in 1892 and an MD in 1896, and Homer Safford's sister, Ada Murray Safford, attended UM from 1896 to 1900. Homer E. and Gertrude S. Safford's daughters Mildred H. Safford and Helen Safford (later Toohy) both received their AB degrees in 1923. Also, Truman Sunderland Safford attended UM with his sisters Mildred and Helen during 1920-1921, before moving on to Antioch College with Mildred. Finally, Clifford M. Toohy (Helen Safford Toohy's husband) attended Michigan for an AB in 1917 and for his law degree in 1920. Moreover, Gertrude's mother, Eliza Jane Read Sunderland (1839-1910), and siblings, Edson Sunderland (1874-1959) and Florence Sunderland (?-1925), received degrees from the University.
Gertrude Sunderland Safford was born in Northfield Massachusetts, but left in 1878 when the Sunderlands moved to Ann Arbor. Before her marriage, she studied under John Dewey at the University of Michigan, as did her mother. After graduation from the University, Gertrude Sunderland followed Dewey to Chicago, where she worked in his experimental school. After marrying Homer E. Safford, Sunderland Safford settled in Detroit. Following in her mother's distinguished footsteps, Sunderland Safford was also a prominent figure in women's activism. In addition to tenures in executive positions in several women's clubs in the first half of the Twentieth Century, Sunderland Safford also served as the founding president of the Wayne County League of Women Voters (an outgrowth of the Detroit League of Women Voters) in 1924. Continuing her interest in education, Sunderland Safford was the first female board member of the Merrill-Palmer School, a position she held for over forty years.
After marriage, Homer E. Safford was a general practitioner in Detroit. Among his works were efforts to reform the Detroit medical system, including a fact-finding tour with Dr. William Metcalf to European and U.S. hospitals as part of a project to plan the new Detroit General Hospital. (This project eventually became the Henry Ford Hospital, after Ford took over the project and threw out the original designs.) Safford left his practice to volunteer for the Army Medical Corps during World War I at Fort Leavenworth, where he served in the neuro-psychiatric division studying 'maladjusted' soldiers. (Among other topics, his letters home refer to the influenza epidemic of that time period.) Safford's experiences during WWI led him into psychiatry. Homer Safford's later work focused on helping 'problem children', especially in the Highland Park school system.
Safford's sister, Ada Murray Safford, was one of Detroit's first public health nurses. She was also an avid genealogist, and compiled historical information and genealogical charts on the Murray and Safford families reaching back to their pre-colonial pasts in England.
The collection also touches on the lives of Homer E. and Gertrude S. Safford's four children. Their eldest daughter, Helen Sunderland Safford, married Clifford M. Toohy (1895-1951), a Detroit attorney. Mildred H. Safford worked for many years at the Detroit Children's Museum, eventually becoming Assistant Director. The collection is much sparser on the lives of Truman Sunderland Safford (1903-), a lawyer, and of the Sunderland Saffords' youngest daughter, Virginia Safford Arnold (1908-).
The Safford Sunderland Family collection consists of the papers of Gertrude Sunderland Safford, her husband Homer E. Safford, his sister Ada M. Safford, and of two of the Sunderland Saffords' daughters, Helen Safford Toohy and Mildred H. Safford. The papers also contain information on and materials from Gertrude Sunderland Safford's parents, Jabez T. Sunderland and Eliza Jane Read Sunderland; her siblings, Edson Read Sunderland and Florence Sunderland; and the Sunderland Saffords' other two children, Truman Sunderland Safford and Virginia Safford Arnold. Additionally, there is some material from and on Helen Safford Toohy's husband (Clifford M. Toohy) and daughters (Janet Toohy Ferguson and Phyllis Toohy). Finally, the collection contains Ada Murray Safford's extensive genealogical materials on the Murray and Safford families.
The papers are organized into six series arranged by family member: Photographs, Gertrude Sunderland Safford, Homer Erwin Safford, Ada Murray Safford, Mildred Hortense Safford, and Helen Safford Toohy.
Subjects:
Medicine--Michigan.; Safford family.; Sunderland family.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 24th (1862-1865); University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Students.; Women--Michigan--History.; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Safford family.; Canton (Mich.)--Houses.; City Hall (Detroit, Mich.); Grand Haven (Mich.); Interiors--Michigan.; Michigan Central Railroad Depot (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Plymouth (Mich.)--Houses.; Sunderland family.; University of Michigan--Campus.; Whitmore Lake (Mich.)
Contributors:
Safford, Ada Murray, 1877-1951.; Safford, Gertrude Sunderland, 1873-1967.; Safford, Homer Erwin, 1869-1933.; Safford, Mildred Hortense, 1901-; Safford, Winfield Scott, d.1863.; Toohy, Helen Safford, 1899-1997.; Sunderland, Eliza Read, 1839-1910.; Sunderland, Jabez Thomas, 1842-1936.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Photographs, 1826-1985
  The Photographs series (1826-1985) contains photos of several generations of Sunderlands and Saffords. In addition to formal portraits, there are numerous casual images of family gatherings and vacations. Other subjects include Detroit, Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan Campus, family homesteads in Canton Township and Grand Haven, and Mildred H. Safford's photo scrapbook of a European tour. Some of the earliest materials in the series are represented by tintypes and glass plate negatives, as well as by original photographs on cardstock and by reprints on modern photo paper.
  - Sunderland Family portraits, Safford Farm, Clifford M. Toohy, Brackett-Safford Family circa 1900-1945 (Folder UAm)
  - Jabez T. Sunderland circa 1890-1936 (Box 1)
  - Eliza Jane Read Sunderland 1890s (Box 1)
    (Also her brother, Thomas H. Read, reprint of photo from ca. 1865)
  - Edson Read Sunderland circa 1890s (Box 1)
    (Also his daughter, Alice Sunderland Wethy with her son David, 1950)
  - Florence Sunderland 1880s (Box 1)
  - Gertrude Sunderland Safford 1877-1957 (Box 1)
  - Jabez T. and Eliza Read Sunderland with Homer E. and Gertrude S. Safford and their Children circa 1904 (Box 1)
    (Helen, Mildred, and Truman)
  - Homer E. Safford circa 1870s-1919 (Box 1)
    (includes tintype)
  - Ada Murray Safford circa 1890s-1949 (Box 1)
  - Crawford/Safford Family (Siblings, parents, and paternal relatives of Homer E. and Ada M. Safford) circa 1860s-1950 (Box 1)
  - Murray/Horton Family (Maternal relatives of Homer E. and Ada M. Safford) (Box 1)
    includes reprints of photos originally from mid-19th century and 1826
  - Homer E. and Gertrude S. Safford circa 1896-1940 (Box 1)
    (Also family gatherings of Homer and Gertrude with their children and grandchildren, some also include Jabez T. Sunderland)
  - Children of Homer E. and Gertrude S. Safford circa 1900-1915, 1976 (Box 1)
    (Helen, Mildred, Truman, and Virginia)
  - Mildred H. Safford circa 1908-1985 (Box 1)
  - Mildred H. Safford's European Tour 1920s (Box 1)
  - Truman S. Safford 1904-1976 (Box 1)
    (Also his first wife, Naomi Brackett Safford, their children Newell and Mary/Molly, and his second wife, Eleanor Safford)
  - Virginia Safford Arnold circa 1930-1945 (Box 1)
    (Also her husband, Orlan M. Arnold, and their children)
  - Helen Safford Toohy 1899-1955 (Box 1)
  - Safford Toohy Family circa 1938-1949, circa 1960s (Box 1)
    (Helen Safford Toohy and her daughters, Janet and Phyllis, and her grandchildren)
  - Martin Toohy Family 1897-1929 (Box 1)
    (Relatives of Clifford M. Toohy, Helen Safford Toohy's husband)
  - Safford Family Farm (And nearby grave plot, both in Plymouth, MI) 1886-1939 (Box 1)
    (includes glass plate negatives)
  - Ann Arbor circa 1890s (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan circa 1880s-1890s (Box 1)
  - Detroit 1891-1932 (Box 1)
  - Grand Haven (Safford Toohy family cottage), early 1900s, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous circa 1890s (Box 1)
- Gertrude Sunderland Safford 1880s-1969
  In addition to extensive family correspondence, the Gertrude Sunderland Safford (1880s-1969) series contains records of Sunderland Safford's involvement with women's clubs, the League of Women Voters, and the Merrill-Parker School. The series also contains records documenting Sunderland Safford's interest in music and diaries of trips to Europe and from her time in Chicago working under John Dewey. Sunderland Safford corresponded quite frequently with her parents, siblings, and children (when they were away); the incoming half of these exchanges are well represented in this series. Of special interest are letters documenting the growth of her children (from the Sunderlands' joy at their births to the children's' letters home from college), Homer Safford's trips away from home (including his tours of European, U.S., and Canadian hospitals and his WWI service), and her father's ongoing involvement with the Unitarian Church and his 1913-1914 trip to Japan and India. The series also includes correspondence addressed to the Sunderland Safford children while they lived at home.
  - Biographical 1890-1967 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - From Various 1888-1964, undated (Box 1)
    - From Lucy Textor 1891-1896, 1933 (Box 1)
    - From Eliza Jane Read Sunderland 1891-1909 (Box 1)
    - From Edson and Florence Sunderland 1891-1926, 1958, undated (Box 2)
    - From Jabez T. Sunderland 1891-1936 (Box 2)
    - From Homer E. Safford 1895-1919, undated, 4 folders (Box 2)
      (partially transcribed)
    - From Various Sunderlands and Saffords (including grandchildren) 1900-1960, undated (Box 2)
    - To Gertrude S. Safford (or to Gertrude S. and Homer E. Safford) from their Children 1902-1969, undated, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Diaries, 1888-1890, 1895-1930, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Personal and Professional Interests
    - Sketchbook 1880s-1890s (Box 3)
    - Letters of Recommendation 1895-1898 (Box 3)
    - Musical Interests 1898-1939 (Box 3)
    - Twentieth Century Club and League of Women Voters 1906-1951 (Box 3)
    - First Unitarian Church Sunday School 1911-1919 (Box 3)
    - The Merrill-Palmer School 1918-1963 (Box 3)
    - Women's City Club
      - Magazine 1928-1942 (Box 3)
      - Bulletin and Annual Report Summary 1921-1924 (Box 3)
      - Programs and Club Activities 1920-1931, undated (Box 3)
  - Various Family Members
    - Letters to the Sunderland Safford Children (Helen, Mildred, Truman, and Virginia), from Family Members 1902-1916, undated (Box 3)
    - Letters to the Sunderland Safford Children (Truman and Virginia), from Family Members 1917-1929, 1940, 1944, undated (Box 3)
    - Obituaries of Eliza Read Sunderland 1910 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Homer Erwin Safford 1843-1982
  Above all, the Homer Erwin Safford (1843-1982) series documents Safford's medical career. This includes his general practice in the 1900s, his work on efforts to build a new hospital in Detroit before WWI, his service in the Army Medical Corps during the War, and his later work as a psychiatric consultant for the Highland Park school system, the Children's Aid Society, various juvenile court systems, and others. Much of these papers are in the form of diaries, correspondence, and clippings on Safford's accomplishments. The series also contains Safford's personal correspondence from family and friends. This includes letters from Gertrude Sunderland Safford both before their marriage and while he was away, and letters from his children. Letters addressed to both parents are included in the Gertrude Sunderland Safford series; because these two series include the children's letters home from while they were away at college, the family correspondence in them is especially rich in documenting student life during the 1920s. Finally, the series includes papers on Safford family history, including ante-bellum and Civil War correspondence.
  - Biographical
    - General 1894-1934, 1982 (Box 3)
    - WWI Reminiscences (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - From Gertrude Sunderland (later Safford) 1896-1918 (Box 3)
    - To and From Various 1898-1924 (Box 3)
    - From His Children 1902-1926, undated (Box 3)
    - To Homer E. and Gertrude S. Safford (From Valentin Block) 1913-1914 (Box 4)
  - Diaries
    - 1908 1909, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Transcripts of 1908, 1909 Diaries (Box 4)
      (with two pages of 1910 diary)
  - Personal and Professional Interests
    - Medical Career Correspondence 1919-1933 (Box 4)
    - Medical Career Publications and Clippings 1901, 1916, 1919-1931, undated (Box 4)
    - WWI Medical Psychiatric Service 1917-1919 (Box 4)
  - Various Family Members
    - Safford Family History (Box 4)
    - Murray/Safford Correspondence 1843-1863 (Box 4)
      (including Civil War letters from Winfield Scott Safford to Robert Crawford Safford)
- Ada Murray Safford 1890s-1951
  The Ada Murray Safford (1890s-1951) series revolves around her significant interest in family history. Records on her career as a public health nurse are dwarfed by correspondence from her 'immediate family' of Sunderland Saffords. These letters, in turn, are outweighed by her extensive correspondence from members of the extended Murray and Safford families on genealogical matters.
  - Biographical 1890s-1951 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Immediate Family 1894-1951 (Box 4)
      (To Ada and her mother from Robert C. Safford, Homer E. and Gertrude S. Safford, and their children)
    - From Various 1931, 1947-1950, undated (Box 4)
  - Clippings on Immediate Family 1901-1950 (Box 4)
  - Nursing Activities 1903-1927 (Box 4)
  - Genealogy
    - Correspondence from Extended Family on Family History 1903-1950, undated (Box 4)
    - Safford/Crawford/Murray/Horton "Common Binder" and other Mixed Records (Box 4)
    - Safford Family (Box 4)
    - Crawford Family, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Crawford/Albright Family (Box 5)
    - Murray/Horton Family (Box 5)
    - Murray/Yard/Horton/Beakes Family (Box 5)
    - Genealogical Associations, Forms and Correspondence (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Mildred Hortense Safford 1903-1983
  Like the other series in the collection, the Mildred Hortense Safford (1903-1987) series is strong on family correspondence, especially for 1918-1925. (This series includes not only correspondence to Mildred Safford, but also correspondence addressed to both Helen and Mildred Safford from during the time when they were at UM together.) Later correspondence includes letters from life-long friends Safford made with sorority sisters and from coworkers at the Detroit Children's Museum. (Some of the sorority sisters' letters to Safford are addressed to 'Peter', a sorority nickname of hers.) The series also documents Safford's distinguished career at the Detroit Children's Museum and her involvement with the Detroit Women's City Club.
  - Biographical 1903-1933, undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondence
    - From Family 1917-1983, undated, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - To Mildred and Helen at College 1919-1923, undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - From Various 1915-1969, undated, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Detroit Children's Museum 1930-1987, undated (Box 6)
  - Women's City Club 1960s-1979 (Box 6)
- Helen Safford Toohy 1899-1976
  The Helen Safford Toohy (1899-1976) series again contains extensive family correspondence, focusing on her years during and immediately following college. Other correspondence includes letters from future husband Clifford M. Toohy. The series also contains records of her educational progress, from her parents' records of her first several dozen words to her notes on University classes. Additionally, the series contains Safford Toohy's diaries documenting her troubled home life with her husband. Finally, the series contains some papers belonging to Clifford Toohy, as well as the letters he received from Helen Safford before their marriage, and letters from various Sunderlands and Saffords to the Safford Toohys' daughter, Janet Toohy, during her first year at Antioch College.
  - Biographical
    - General 1899-1926, undated (Box 6)
    - School Work and Honors 1900s-1923 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - From Various 1917-1952, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - From Family 1918-1963, undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - From Clifford M. Toohy 1924-1925 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Outgoing Correspondence 1941-1952 (Box 6)
  - Diaries 1907, 1915, 1921-1922, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Diaries 1927, 1927-1937 (Box 7)
  - Detroit Symphony 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Family Clippings 1936-1976 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Clifford M. Toohy
    - Correspondence (From Helen Safford) 1924-1940, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Church Materials 1940-1941 (Box 7)
  - Janet Safford Toohy (later Ferguson)
    - Correspondence (From family) 1945-1946 (Box 7)
Researchers interested in more about the Sunderlands may also wish to consult other material held by the Bentley Historical Library: Alice Sunderland Wethy's A Genealogical-Biographical Compilation of the Sunderland and Broadhead Families (Bentley Historical Library call number DB/2/S958/W539/v.2), as well as the Jabez T. Sunderland, Eliza Jane Read Sunderland, Edson Read Sunderland, and Florence Sunderland collections.